# 刚哥
Hey bro
# 诶 兄弟
Hey
#我給你帶了一隻竹鼠 放在這邊
I've brought you 3 bamboo rats. Right here
# 哇 这只好凶啊
whoa, this one is so fierce
# 竹鼠来了
The bamboo rats have come!
# 竹鼠來了
Bamboo rats there are
# 什么时候到的
When did you arrive?
# 刚到
We just arrived
# 你看它在干嘛
Have a look - what is it doing?
# 这个好凶
Very hostile, this one
# 要不我们搞点竹子给它吃
How about getting it some bamboos
# 对 我这里有竹子
Good idea. I have bamboo planted here.
# 哪里有竹子
Where are the bamboos?
# 我们家那么多竹子你不知道吗
How comes that you don't know our family have got quite a lot bamboos
# 你也太客气了吧又带3只竹鼠过来
It's so kind of you to bring three more bamboo rats
# 没事儿自家养的
No worries, they are all raised by me
# 我把它劈一下吧
let me cleave them
# （缺失）
These bamboos are the favourite of bamboo rats
# 它们这几天都饿坏了
They have been starving these days
# 小心啊
Careful
# 好凶啊这个
They are so fierce now
# 我给你说它是不会认主人的哦
I tell you, they are not ganna recognize a master
# 咦 好凶啊
why so hostile
# 好霸道啊
So aggressive
# 这样可是不行的哟 这么霸道
It should not be like this. It's being too aggressive
# 对吧
right?
# 晚上我们把它那个了
Let's do that tonight
# 哪个
what
# 你这边有没有烧烤架
Do you have a grill
# 有啊
Of course
# 可以哟
Nice
# 先把它烤了再说
Let's roast this one first
# 不然这2个早上起来会受伤的
Otherwise, you will find the other two hurted tomorrow morning
# 小心哦 小心手哦
take care, watch your hands
# 那么凶
so fierce!
# 嘿 出来啦
Hey you're out
# 出来一只
one got out!
one got out
# 拉它尾巴就可以了
just grab its tail
# 咦呀
whoa
# 好凶啊 好凶啊
such a hostile one!
# 好肥呀
It is so fat
# 嗯
um
# 这个放进去了哦
I'm going to put this one in there
# 那么凶
too fierce
# 不管怎么说
anyway
# 竹子还是给它吃
we need to feed it bamboos
# 我带你参观一下我们家
Let me show you around my house
# 好啊
good good
# 那么漂亮的房子
Such a pretty house
# 现在就是这个样子砖房
So now it looks like this, a brick house
# 可以呀
looks good
# 很凉快的哦 这样的房子
This kind of house can be very cool
# 以前是土屋嘛
It was once built by soil (?
# 冬暖夏凉的
Warm in winter and cool in summer
# 费了很大的功夫
It took quite a lot efforts to build
# 这个是水井
This is our well
# 这个水井几十年了
been here for many a ten years
# 来我给你压
Let me pump some water for you
# 你洗下手吧
You can wash your hands
# 我来我来
I will handle this
# 哇 这个水好凉快哦
wow, the water is so cool
# 别的东西没有水倒是很多
We have tuns of water and nothing else
# 来 你来压我来洗
Your turn, let me wash my hands
# 好啦好啦
Okay okay
# 够啦
it's enough
# 这井水好凉快
this well water is nicely chill
# 谁家的鸭子
Whose ducks are they?
# 这个是我家养的
They are mine
# 你看都长大了
See, they are full-grown
# 现在还小还不能吃
Still too small for us to eat
# 现在才三四斤等喂到四五斤再吃
only weigh 3 to 4 jin (jin: 500g), I'm gonna wait until they grow as heavy as 4 to 5 jin
# 太小了它的毛不好拔
It is hard to remove the feathers from tiny ducks
# 对
true
# 其实你早点来就好了
If only you come here earlier
# 早点来我们下面那块田里的稻谷都还没打
when we have not harvested the crops from that field
# 嘿嘿嘿
hahah
# 割稻谷我也会哦
I know how to cut the crops too
# 不过你来得也正是时候
But still you come here just on time!
# 我这里有一块地
I have a piece of field here
# 准备给它翻一下
am just thinking about plowing it
# 听说你干农活儿很厉害
heard that you are extremely good at farmworks
# 对呀
you are right
# 别的不多说锄头我都给你准备好了
No need to say more, I got the pickaxe for you
# 你看那边是我种的小葱
You see, those are scallions planted by me
# 哇那么漂亮
whoa, they look so pretty
# 你看吧我边上都挖了中间给你留了一块
See, I've plowed the area at the sides and left the middle part for you
# 这个没问题啊
No problem
# 小问题
little thing
# 漆二娃把锄头拿过来
take me the pickaxe Qi Er Wa
# 反正来都来了就干点会儿嘛
You are already here, why not help us with some farmworks?
# 可以
Alright
# 种点青菜
Plant some veggies
# 种点那个水果
some fruits
# （缺失）
Let's see who will be the first to finish
# 西红柿之类的
something like tomatoes
# 好啊 看谁先挖好
Okay, let's see!
# 怎么不养几只鸡在这里
why don't you raise some chickens here
# 养点小动物出来嘛
Some little animals
# 鸡养着有啊
We do have chickens
# 有啊
you do
# 但是还小啊
but they are still small
# 那我来早了哦
I am a bit too early
# 对啊
true
# 快过年的时候再来一次
I will come here again around the Spring Festival
# 可以啊
welcome!
# 要多养点那些小动物出来哦
I tell you, do raise more little animals
# 鸡呀 鸭呀 鹅呀
like chickens, ducks, and geese
# 休息会儿呗
have some rest
# 可以啊
Okay
# 再坚持几分钟
A few more minutes
# 通通帮你全部翻掉
and all will be done
# 我就喜欢听你这句话来继续干
This is what I am expecting, keep on!
# 多种点菜
Grow more veggies
# 到時候青菜都直接可以在這裡摘
and you can pick right here when you need them
# 休息会儿
take a break
# 累不累
Are you tired
# 有一点累
a little
# 这个比爬山轻松多了
This is more relaxing than climbing mountains
# 爬山更累
which is more exhaustive
# （缺失）
Is it?
# 对
Yep
# 这个不那么累
This is less tiring
# 但是也会累啊
But you can still feel the fatigue
# 哇 搞定
Whoa, it's done!
# 终于翻过来了
It's all plowed finally
# 我那边还有几亩地
I still got several mu over there (mu: 0.165 acre)
# 下次我牵条牛来帮你把它犁一下
Next time I take a cow to help you plow them
# 辛苦了兄弟
Thanks a lot bro
# 没事啊
It's alright
# 这个土才到哪啊 还多得很
There are still a lot to do